Gwen Reed
Hartford History Center, Hartford Public Library
Gwen Reed Collection
1936-1974 (Bulk Dates)
Hartford History Center, Hartford Public Library Hartford, Connecticut
Reed, Gwendolyn B. (Clarke)
3 linear feet (6 boxes)
Papers of noted Hartford actress Gwen Reed.
Biographical Note
Gwendolyn B. Clarke was born in 1912 to Georgianna and George Nathaniel Clarke of New York City. Georgianna soon left her husband, and she and her daughter settled in Hartford in 1921. Both worked in the tobacco fields, but Gwen also graduated from Arsenal Elementary School and Hartford Public High School. She briefly attended Hartford Federal College before marrying John T. Reed in 1935. The couple separated a few years later and were divorced by 1948.
In October 1936, the Charles Gilpin Players formed, with Gwen as their secretary. She began her acting career with the Charles Gilpin players as well, with a role in the June 1937 performance of "Trilogy in Black." Over the years Gwen performed in and directed numerous productions in Hartford. In 1946 she began a 17 year tenure portraying Aunt Jemima for the Quaker Oats Company. Gwen traveled all over New England promoting the brand.
In Hartford, Gwen was dedicated to educational and community work. She made television appearances on Channel 3's children's program "Ranger Station," originated the Playtime for Tots program in Bellevue Square, as well as teaching in the Head Start and Reading is Fundamental Programs.
Following Gwen Reed's death in 1974, Hartford Mayor George A. Athanson dedicated a storytelling room to Gwen at the Ropkins Branch of the Hartford Public Library.
Scope and Content
Papers of Gwen Reed, a Hartford tobacco worker turned actress, educator, and community worker. Included are papers from her involvement with Community Players, Hartford Stage Company, and Playtime for Tots. Theater programs and scripts constitute about a third of the collection. A valuable source of information is Reed's scrapbook from her time with the Charles Gilpin Players (1936-1939), a beneficiary of the Federal Theater Project. Reed is also well known for having portrayed Aunt Jemima throughout New England during a 17-year career with the Quaker Oats Company. Additional material includes photographs, a video tape from WFSB Channel 3, and plaques.
Access Restrictions
The records are stored in a restricted area and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
Accruals
The collection is closed. Additional accruals are not expected.
Subject Headings
Personal Names
Jemima, Aunt
Corporate Names
Quaker Oats Company; Charles Gilpin Players; Federal Theatre Project (U.S.)
Subjects
African American women; Photographs; Drama; Actresses - Hartford
Genre Terms
Scrapbooks
Contents:
- Papers
  - African American Studies (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Associated Little Theaters of Greater Hartford, 1949-51 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Aunt Jemima (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Charles Gilpin Players (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Clark, George (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Community Players (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Community Players, Applications (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Community Players, Correspondence, 1948-51 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Community Players, Minutes, 1948-51 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Community Renewal Team of Hartford (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1939-74 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Hartford Public Schools (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Hartford Stage Company (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Parade for Freedom-A Dedication to Frederick Douglas, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Performances, Clippings (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Playtime for Tots (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Playtime for Tots, Applications (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Playtime for Tots, Class of, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Playtime for Tots, Events and News (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Playtime for Tots, Time Sheets (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Programs, 1946-49 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Programs, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Programs, 1951-56 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Programs, 1957-74, ND (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Reading for Fun, Damental (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Reed, Gwen, Biographical (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Reed, Gwen,Calendars, 1970-71 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Reed, Gwen, Certificates and Awards (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Reed, Gwen, Hartford Public Library (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Reed, Gwen, Memberships/Organizations (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Reed, Gwen, Personal Records (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - A Salute to Gwen Reed, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Script, Anderson, Maxwell, Bad Seed (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Script, Applegarth, Margaret T., The Legion of the Black Madonna (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Script, Armstrong, William Howard, Sounder (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Script, Barry, Spranger, Cupid's Bow, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Script, Brownell, John Charles, Mississippi Rainbow, circa 1935-39 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Script, Coleman, Ralf, The Double Take, ND (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Script, Coleman, Warren, The Greener Grass, ND (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Script, Davis, Allen, On Vengence Height, 1924 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Script, France, Anatole, The Man Who Married a Dumb Wife, 1915 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Green, Paul, The Man Who Died at Twelve O'Clock, 1925-31 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Script, Gunderson, Lee, A Moment of Hope (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Script, Hellman, Lillian, The Little Foxes, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Script, Herliby, Ludvig, Jeppe of the Hill, 1722 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Script, Hurd, Reggie Jr., The Age of Anguish, ND (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Script, Hurd, Reggie Jr., The Red Tie, ND (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Script, Hurd, Reggie Jr., Savior From Agnew Alley, ND (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Script, Huxley, Aldous, The Gioconda Smile, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Script, Kotz, Kathleen Murphy, Five Favorite Folk Plays, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Script, Manley, William Ford, Sacrifice, ND (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Script, Manley, William Ford, Samson and Delilah (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Script, McCullers, Carson, The Member of the Wedding, Broadway opening 1950 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Script, McCoo, Edward, Ethopia at the Bar of Justice (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Script, O'Neil, Eugene, Before Breakfast, 1916 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Script, Reed, Gwen, Get Your Morning Paper (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Script, Reed, Gwen, Home, Sweet Home (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Script, Reed, Gwen, Ripping Quarters (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Script, Reed, Gwen, The Test (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Script, Reed, Gwen, 3 Peas One Pod (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Script, Russel, Charlie L, Five on the Back Hand Side (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Script, Ryerson, Florence and Colin Clements, Last Night, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Script, Stone, Gene and Jack Robinson, Ready! Aim! Fire! (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Script, Williams, Tennessee, The Glass Menagerie (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Script, Williams, Tennessee, Talk to Me Like the Rain and Let Me Listen (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Script, Author unknown, And No One Asked: A Choral (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Script, Author unknown, Bitter Bread (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Script, Author unknown, Broadcast of 1950 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Script, Author unknown, The Courage and the Grace (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Script, Author unknown, Father to the Man (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Script, Author unknown, For Better or Worse (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Script, Author unknown, Two Birds (With One Stone) (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Photographs (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Photographs (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Photographs (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Photographs (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Photographs (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Oversized Portrait (Box 5)
  - Award (Box 5)
  - Gwen Reed Week Proclamination, 1975 (Box 5)
  - Songbook, "Let's Sing Again" (Box 5)
  - Scrapbook, Programs (Box 5)
  - Scrapbook, "The Sincere Testimony to Anxiety, Labor, Patience, Time and Cordial, Constructive Critism and to Memories Turbulent or Tender of Conn. Federal Theater, October 1936 to May 6, 1939 (Box 5)
  - Plaques (Box 6)
  - Video Tape: WFSB TV, "Gwen Reed (Box 6)
  - Keys to Cities (Box 6)